<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Nolan Nichols - Conferences</title><link href="https://www.nolan-nichols.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.nolan-nichols.com/feeds/conferences.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.nolan-nichols.com/</id><updated>2015-09-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>NIDM and NCANDA at Neuroinformatics 2015</title><link href="https://www.nolan-nichols.com/ni2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-09-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Nolan Nichols</name></author><id>tag:www.nolan-nichols.com,2015-09-21:/ni2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A brief summary of my role at Neuroinformatics 2015 including the pre-meeting&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NIDM Workshop and a talk I presents during the investigator session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year the annual &lt;a href="http://www.neuroinformatics2015.org"&gt;Neuroinformatics Congress&lt;/a&gt; took place in
tropical &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cairns"&gt;Cairns, Austrailia&lt;/a&gt;, where I had the opportunity to lead a pre-meeting
workshop on the Neuroimaging Data Model (&lt;a href="http://nidm.nidash.org"&gt;NIDM&lt;/a&gt;) and present the data integration
framework developed for the National Consortium on Alcohol NeuroDevelopment in
Adolescence (&lt;a href="http://ncanda.org"&gt;NCANDA&lt;/a&gt;). Below you can find highlights and links to a few resources
I've made available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NIDM Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NIDM Workshop took place over two days where I was able to sit down with around 10
participants and my fellow NIDM Developers from the International Neuroinformatics
Coordinating Facility (&lt;a href="http://incf.org/"&gt;INCF&lt;/a&gt;) Neuroimaging Data Sharing (&lt;a href="http://wiki.incf.org/mediawiki/index.php/Neuroimaging_Task_Force"&gt;NIDASH&lt;/a&gt;) Task Force. We
put together a number of training materials before workshop in the form
of &lt;a href="https://jupyter.org/"&gt;Jupyter Notebooks&lt;/a&gt; that are available on our &lt;a href="https://github.com/incf-nidash/nidm-training"&gt;nidm-trianing&lt;/a&gt; Github repo. The
training materials provide an introduction to NIDM and our use of the &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/prov-overview/"&gt;W3C PROV&lt;/a&gt;
standards to represent provenance and metadata from neuroimaging studies. I'll detail
NIDM in another blog post, but briefly we use &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semantic_Web"&gt;Semantic Web Standards&lt;/a&gt; to formalize
terms and vocabulary used to share brain imaging data. Additionally, Semantic Web tools
provide a useful framework for data integration. For example, I created
a &lt;a href="https://github.com/incf-nidash/nidm-training/blob/master/use-cases/integration-queries/ABIDE_FBIRN_Query.ipynb"&gt;simple example of integrating two datasets&lt;/a&gt; that use that use different labels
for the same information. Finally, I worked on a converter to generate a NIDM document
from a medical imaging database that is (currently) open as a &lt;a href="https://github.com/incf-nidash/nidm/pull/340"&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt; on the
NIDM Github repo. This was the first time our group presented to this material in an
educational setting, which was great fun and incredibly helpful to hear additional use
cases and example applications!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NCANDA Presentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Investigator Presentations session, there was strong representation from the
NIDASH Task Force of which I was one. First, the
overall &lt;a href="http://www.frontiersin.org/Community/AbstractDetails.aspx?ABS_DOI=10.3389/conf.fnins.2015.91.00004&amp;amp;eid=2602&amp;amp;sname=Neuroinformatics_2015"&gt;NIDM framework was presented&lt;/a&gt; by David Keator that details how to model
neuroimaging study metadata, identify terms from ontologies, and contribute feedback and
suggestions back to the task force. Similarly, Chris Gorgolewski presented on a standard
for organizing brain imaging data into a directory structure that tools can operate off
of in a common way, which is called the &lt;a href="http://www.frontiersin.org/Community/AbstractDetails.aspx?ABS_DOI=10.3389/conf.fnins.2015.91.00056&amp;amp;eid=2602&amp;amp;sname=Neuroinformatics_2015"&gt;Brain Imaging Data Structure&lt;/a&gt;. In
my &lt;a href="http://www.frontiersin.org/Community/AbstractDetails.aspx?ABS_DOI=10.3389/conf.fnins.2015.91.00042&amp;amp;eid=2602&amp;amp;sname=Neuroinformatics_2015"&gt;own presentation&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed a framework we've been working on to
harmonize &lt;a href="http://xnat.org"&gt;XNAT&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://project-redcap.org/"&gt;REDCap&lt;/a&gt; using a collection of Python scripts that perform
a variety of data transformations into a common data model based on REDCap.
Additionally, the system automates image processing and scoring of
clinical/neuropsychological measures. Currently, I'm working to now incorporate NIDM and
BIDS into the NCANDA framework to demonstrate how these standards can be used in the
wild. You can check out my presentation below and let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{% youtube RduYPL82K64 %}&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Conferences"></category><category term="neuroinformatics"></category><category term="nidm"></category><category term="data sharing"></category><category term="ncanda"></category></entry></feed>